It's not good to chase status symbols.
So if something is not something that
you personally enjoy, but you want to
signal to others, that's usually not the
best use of money.
>> The biggest asset that rich people have
or poor people.
>> One of the biggest resources that rich
people have is the ability to short the
currency. If there are people that lack
a better options holding currency that
you're shorting, you're kind of
gradually extracting value from that.
They're shorting the thing that other
people are earning their wages in. The
basement is historically a type of tax
that developed countries will be growing
at historically 6 to 8% per year. uh in
developing countries it's it's often
over 10%. Everybody's savings are
getting debased. As you increase the
money supply, those who are on the right
side of deficits uh are doing pretty
well and those who are not receiving the
deficits are the ones getting debased.
Always kind of ask the question, am I
being diluted? In a lot of economic
circles, you you'll hear that, okay,
barter existed. Uh that's filled with
frictions and so people invented money
to get around that problem. But then
there's some push back against that by
people pointing out that actual barter
was fairly rare in history.
>> Money is a big part of our life. Most
people struggle to answer the most basic
question.
What is money?
>> She's the queen of the game. Stacking
crypto like it's her claim to fame. If
you want success, then take a look away.
>> Okay, today I'm so happy. Oh my god. I'm
joined by Lynn Elden, one of the most
trusted voices in macro and finance. Um,
she has a very rare background in both
engineering and finance and known for
making sense of how money, debt, and
technology shape our world in a way that
everyday people can understand. And she
was the lead engineer, correct me if I'm
wrong, at the FAA's cockpit simulation
facility before um launching.
>> Yeah. So cool. before launching Lynn
Elden investment strategy and her book
broken money walk us through the past
present and the future of money and you
know her work has been featured on CNBC
the W wall Wall Street Journal and of
course now finally on Bonnie Botching so
excited I've been dying to have you on
the show
>> happy to be here happy to be here thanks
for having me
>> there's so much I want to talk about but
I'm hoping that this video could be you
know a really good introduction
of your ideas, your book and knowledge
to the Chinese speaking world and then
I'll have an excuse to have you on
again.
>> Sure.
>> So, first question, uh, money is a big
part of our lives, right? But you know
how most people struggle to answer the
most basic question, what is money?
>> Yeah, good question. Uh, so I argue in
the book that money is a ledger. Uh, and
basically what that does is that kind of
combines two theories of what money is.
Uh so in one camp basically there's
commodity money. Uh the idea that you
know people basically find a commodity
that works pretty well as money. It's
divisible. It's portable. It's
fungeable. It's pretty hard to make more
of. Uh you know different different
commodity monies come in contact with
each other and the best one wins. Uh
that historically became gold and
silver. Uh that that's kind of one camp
of what money is. Uh the other one is
the idea that money is credit. Uh they
you don't often even need to exchange
physical things. uh like if you have an
economy where someone makes bread and
someone makes uh beef. Um basically you
can you can you know get the the bread
uh maker can buy beef and then give
bread credits uh to the you know the
butcher and then he that person can go
and redeem them for bread at a later
time. So it's kind of it smooths out
trade. Uh and what they both have in
common is that they're basically
ledgers. Uh and so commodity money uses
nature as a ledger. Um and uh credit
uses either informal groups as the
basically the ones maintaining the
ledger or on a larger scale institutions
and governments maintaining that ledger.
Uh and one of the things I focus on in
broken money is that technology can
substantially change what makes sense to
use as a ledger. Uh and so one of the
things I kind of emphasize in the book
uh is that prior to the
telecommunication age, some types of
monies made sense and post the telecom
age, which of course we're in now, uh
substantially changes what works as
money.
>> So you talked about credit and there is
an idea I find really interesting that
you wrote in the book, flexible social
credit. So this goes back to the
history, right? people keep track of who
is helpful in the society and who's a
burden and you know that becomes a
formal credit that affects um how easy
people participate in um financial
activities. Um can you explain that
idea?
>> Sure. And that that was basically I was
tackling a concept that comes up
sometimes in economic debates. Uh which
is in a lot of economic circles you
you'll hear that okay barter existed uh
that's filled with frictions and so
people invented money to get around that
problem. But then there's some push back
against that by people pointing out that
actual barter was fairly rare in history
based on uh what we know of history and
what we even can study from hunter
gatherers. uh that generally speaking
there's there's relatively low volumes
of barter and that intend to rely on
credit as the actual medium of transfer
uh and in very small groups that's very
informal. Uh the example I use in the
book is in the movie Godfather uh Veto
Corleó the the mob boss uh someone comes
and asks him for a favor in the famous
opening scene of the movie uh and
instead of asking money to do that favor
uh he basically says uh there will be a
time in the future and the future might
never come where I might ask you for a
favor uh and you'll you'll do that favor
for me. So, so basically the an exchange
happened nothing physically traded hands
uh but it was saying in the future I
might call on you and that you know
outside of the moth context that is that
is common in friend groups that is
common in neighbor groups that was
common in hunter hunter gather groups
based on current and historical
evidence. Uh and then as you go up the
um uh stack of economic complexity you
start to institutionalize that more. you
start to have uh third-party arbittors
that basically enforce laws or enforce
uh claims like that. And that's
basically how we've historically built
the financial stack.
>> Do you think that's fair? Because if
someone is actually helpful for this
society, then that person should be able
to get, you know, financial help or
participate in financial activities
easier. I think that sounds fair.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I mean that's that's a
normal it's a it's part of the incentive
structure of working in groups. Uh that
basically when when when things are
going well for you, you try to give more
than you get out of it because you know
there's there's could be some future
time where you're impaired in some way
uh and you might need other people to
help you. And if you've had a history of
of providing a surplus, you're more
likely to to be given aid when you when
you need to, you know, be given a
surplus. And then of course there's
different social structures for some
people are in a position where they just
they can't uh realistically provide a
surplus through no fault of their own.
Uh family helps them out and so it
becomes relying on someone who's who's
associated with that person to provide a
surplus uh or certain you know certain
types of um things that are considered
acceptable to help each other in uh
which different societies navigate. Um
but basically you know uh both
reputation wise uh but then also when
you when you expand the groups don't
even know people anymore. Liquid money
just kind of serves as the glue that
ties a lot of that together as people
seek what they're really after, which is
other types of capital, shelter, food,
um, entertainments, uh, luxuries, things
like that. And the ledgers we use are
basically a way of communicating between
ourselves, how we acquire those and how
we transfer those.
>> And you also talked about how telecom
and money has this interesting
relationship
in the book.
>> Yeah. So prior to the invention of the
telegraph which happened in in the 1830s
and it really wasn't deployed in long
distances to like the 1860s and
worldwide didn't hit till the 1900s but
before that time period uh basically as
different commodity monies came in
contact with each other so shells and
copper and livestock and whatever people
might use as money uh as they all kind
of came together as all the different
cultures found each other it was really
gold and silver that emerged as the the
best ones. uh bec and and the the main
metric there is high stock toflow
ratios. Basically things that are very
long lasting, divisible, portable, and
very very hard to substantially increase
the supply of uh even as we get better
at making more tools, as we get more
industrialized, it's still hard to make
gold, for example, to mine more gold and
refine it out of the ground compared to,
you know, industrial processes of
getting shells or other types of
commodities. Uh and so for for the
longest time for thousands of years
people gravitated toward the monies that
have the best characteristics mainly in
terms of of liquid scarcity. Um the big
gamecher that happened uh is the
invention of the telegraph and then
subsequently of course the telephone uh
radio internet all these other
technologies uh which is suddenly speed
mattered. Prior to that all these
commodities moved around at roughly the
same speed. uh you know shells and gold
can exchange hands roughly at the same
speed. Uh whereas in the telecom era we
we entered a very different types of
ledgers uh where people can make a a
transfer uh over an ocean within seconds
and the physical settlement of something
like gold especially when audited and
and you know the whole process of
legally transferring it can take a very
long period of time and be very
expensive. Uh and so what that did was
that shifted uh global society more
toward bank ledgers, central bank
ledgers and nation state ledgers uh
which really changed the power dynamic
of of how money works and kind of put us
into a new era. Basically we entered a
period where prior to that time
transaction speeds were generally faster
than settlement speeds in the sense that
various technologies like bills of
exchange uh paper bank notes um these
kind of proxies for money they they did
kind of grease the frictions of exchange
um uh but only to a certain degree uh
because you're still literally
exchanging paper instead of exchanging
you know maybe metal coins in some
capacity. Uh but once you have that
telecom component, you dramatically
increase the speed of transactions, but
you still have the problem of final
settlement. Uh who do you rely on to
arbitrate the the ledger without credit?
And so for something like a century and
a half, we were in this period of time
where transaction speeds could move at
the speed of light and settlement speeds
were were still physical, were still
moving at the speed of matter. And not
until the invention of Bitcoin uh and
then the adoption of Bitcoin. So Bitcoin
when it was worth zero still didn't
really matter yet in in a macro scale.
So but once it becomes a you know a
trillion dollar asset it starts to
matter. Uh so we kind of finally closed
the speed gap by you know Satoshi
inventing uh fast settlement. Uh
basically the the ability to send
someone value that can't be pulled back
and is not relying on some sort of
central ledger like a central bank or a
commercial bank uh managing that. Um and
so you know we we kind of can categorize
money into three categories of time. So
one was pre- telecom mostly commodity
money and and and formal credit. Uh then
the middle stage which was kind of this
rise of banking and rise of central
banking. uh and then the current era uh
where you know because the invention of
of Bitcoin uh we now have other methods
to basically decentralize even the
bottom layer and actually start closing
that speed gap that has existed for a
century and a half and has spawned you
know both opportunities and uh downsides
along the way. the three era you talked
about that kind of reminded me of you
know how people used to want to be able
to touch their physical money and later
on now they have this argument of hey
bitcoin is something I cannot see I
cannot smell I cannot touch therefore it
probably doesn't worth that much you
know there are these group of pro gold
people for example people like Peter
Schiff would argue that uh bitcoin is
you're trading nothing basically. That's
what he said.
>> Yeah. I mean, sometimes it's a
generational issue. Uh people people
that grew up more more in our
generation, we I mean fa Facebook, you
know, Meta is a is a you know, multi-
trillion dollar company and and their
product is online. Same thing with, you
know, most of the biggest stocks these
days basically have a primarily online
experience. Now they still have a
physical component like their data
centers but the actual capex for that is
pretty small relative to the total value
and profits of the company which which
most exists uh online. And of course
anyone you know people you know they
they they will pay a lot of money for a
skin in a video game for example uh as a
status symbol or as just as aesthetic
enjoyment uh even though it doesn't
exist in the real world because that's
where people a lot of people spend their
time. They spend hours of time online.
Uh, and Bitcoin I I'd argue is similar,
which is in this telecom connected
world. Um, there's more we can do with
Bitcoin than gold. Uh, not and I' I've
historically I'm a gold bull. I like I
I'm not like in the camp. There are some
people in the camp that say buy Bitcoin,
sell your gold. I'm like, okay, there's
still there's still use for gold as
there's always been. Um, but in the
telecom connected world, we're having
this conversation from, you know, uh,
far apart. Um, and you know, Bitcoin
bridges that gap. you know, we could
send a Bitcoin transaction back and
forth here. We can't do the same thing
with gold without some sort of credit as
an intermediary. Um, and Bitcoin, just
like those big stocks like Facebook and
Google and and you know, Amazon and all
that, Bitcoin still has a physical
presence. Uh, there are still Bitcoin
miners, uh, that, you know, acquire
energy, uh, process it and and, you
know, mine Bitcoin. Uh, there's still
computers running nodes. Um and so there
is a physical component uh which which
makes sense for the world that we live
in. There's there's proof of work. Um
but of course a lot of the value is the
fact that it is digital.
Elsa speak.
Well, I really appreciate that you
answer these questions. I appreciate
your kind words.
Fore,
Elsa Pro, Elsa Premium.
Okay. So on your YouTube channel there
is this excellent video called how money
and banking work and why they're broken
today. So you talk about the three era
gold standard um the bread woods and
petro dollar system. My question is are
we entering this new era of of course
Bitcoin is in the picture but stable
coin is that the next era of US dollar
and how like what role does stable coin
play today?
>> Yeah, I think partially I we can kind of
categorize this there's almost there
there two ends of the spectrum. Uh and
one of my favorite citations in the book
broken money is from William Stanley
Jevans back in 1875. He wrote a book
called Money and the Mechanism of
Exchange. And this was this was right at
the dawn of the of the telegraph era. Uh
he wrote that book like a decade after
the crossatlantic telegraph cable was
put into place. Um and one thing he
pointed out was that almost every
friction in finance is solved by another
layer of centralization. So like if I
want to send you money, uh it helps if
we have the same bank uh because I can
just tell the bank debit my account,
credit your account. if we have
different banks that it helps if our
banks can talk to each other in some way
to make that easier. So, they often tie
into a central bank. Uh, and if we're in
different countries, then it helps if
our central banks talk to each other and
have a way to to either use the same uh
underlying ledger maybe of of a of
whatever the biggest central bank is uh
to move that money around. Uh, and so
there's really kind of like four layers
of centralization uh that we've built up
in the modern financial stack. Um, now
what Bitcoin is is, you know, mo like
most fintech today is like the top
layer. It's it's yet it's a
technological layer that runs on that
whole layered stack. Uh, you know,
fintech companies are are ultimately
still built on banks. Uh, they just
abstract a lot of that away from us. And
stable coins are like that, which is
that they add this kind of top layer of
technological efficiency. Uh, they do
solve a lot of issues. There, you know,
there are over 40 currencies in Africa.
There are over 30 currencies uh in Latin
America. Uh there's plenty of currencies
in Southeast Asia. There there's these
areas where there's there's very
fractured currency markets. Uh and
there's a lot of demand for dollars. Uh
and basically what a stable coin is is
it takes the idea of an offshore bank
account which used to only be available
to the wealthy uh and basically
compresses the the overhead the cost of
doing that and makes that available to
anyone with an internet connection. So
the global uh working middle and upper
middle classes uh and that has that that
has ramifications. Um Bitcoin is
different in the sense that it actually
instead of being a layer on top of that
whole stack, it's a new parallel
foundational layer. Uh so it's basically
uh the way to do central banking but in
a distributed way. Uh so so the ability
to settle final value uh without ongoing
uh there's there's no one there's no
single entity in control of that ledger.
it's the whole group of miners and node
runners uh that dictate how that ledger
works. Uh and so I I do think that
stable coins and you know to some extent
uh CBDC's because there's different
different um different ways to go about
this. They kind of actually serve
similar roles. They're kind of the final
evolution of fiat currency. Um they're
kind of the top of that whole four layer
stack of centralization. uh and that's
coming out of course at the same time
roughly speaking as Bitcoin uh which is
a whole new foundation of a stack to to
build on.
>> So you talk about how there are
different currencies. I want to bring up
Nigeria. So in 2022 Nigerians
uh were told that they could only spend
20 US dollar per week on things outside
of their country and later they're
allowed a little more. I used to go to
Nigeria um and there are two currency
rates. So the black market rate and then
the official rate. But my question will
be let's say USD stable coin is now very
popular everywhere in the world. What
does this new world look like? Do they
still use their currency or is everybody
just relying on US dollar?
>> Well, it gives them a lot of
optionality. Uh so they might not switch
entirely to dollars, but now all of them
have the option uh to access dollars
more easily than they used to. uh and
Bitcoin as well. And so for example, if
if I wanted to hire a Nigerian graphic
designer to do something um before if I
wanted to pay her uh it would be subject
to all these frictions uh that that
official exchange rate would probably
come into play. Uh where basically the
government kind of gets their uh
percentage of it often, you know, I
would I would say unfairly. uh whereas
now she can, you know, she can hold up a
QR code on a video call or send me any
sort of payment string and whether she
wants to be paid in in stable coins or
bitcoin or whatever else um at the
exchange rate that we decide uh you know
between me and that person uh that just
goes around whatever Nigeria wants to
do. Um and so it really depowers the the
the middleman and empowers the people
making individual decisions which I
think is good. Um, one of the, you know,
I I I go to Egypt every year, um, and
they have, they've had similar periods
of time where they have kind of an
artificial peg of their currency with,
you know, like this exchange rate and at
at times that no longer becomes
sustainable and so the the the gray
market starts to deviate from uh, what
the official exchange rate is. So it
might be 30 Egyptian pounds to the
dollar officially. Uh but then at the
same time, if you actually wanted to get
physical dollars on the streets of
Cairo, you're gonna you're gonna pay 50
Egyptian pounds for it. Uh and things
like stable coins uh can go around that.
And Nigeria and Egypt are interesting
examples because they're both among the
most populous countries in Africa. Uh
Nigeria is very much uh far into Bitcoin
and stable coins, very high adoption
rates. Uh Egypt uh is is still low
adoption rates. Uh and basically it it
just kind of shows the example of of how
people can get empowered by the
technology uh to start um you know
protecting themselves from their local
currency debasement uh making
crossborder trade just easier to do if
you're running any sort of business uh
that or remittances uh that involve
flowing across border. So it's, you
know, in in outright currency failure
scenarios, it can involve fully getting
out of the currency, but in many cases
just involves getting part of your value
out of the currency and giving that user
more choice, which over time can chip
away at a at a local national currency.
And I would generally argue that this
this current period we live in with like
180 different currencies that's mostly
an artifact of this weird arbitrage that
exists between fast transactions
historically no way to do fast
settlements. Uh and so we became reliant
on these centralized ledgers. uh but as
the world gets more internet connected
and as these technologies like stable
coins and bitcoins get big and liquid so
not just exist but actually big and
liquid enough and and understood enough
to matter uh it starts to you know
connect all of those and gradually maybe
not immediately but gradually start
making more and more of those currencies
obsolete
um and gravitating you know away from
the weakest ones first probably and then
moving up the stack toward the the
biggest and strongest ones. Um, as as
people want, you know, they have more
choice. They they get out of their local
monopoly with at least some of their
value.
>> Can you explain why countries
do capital control? Cuz sometimes I'm
like, well, is stable coin kind of
against countries interest,
different countries interest? For
example, why does Nigerian government
impose this capital control? Why?
>> Uh so there's a like a trillemma in
currencies where you know a country can
pick its exchange rate. They can pick
its industry rate uh or and or it can
have open capital markets. So so so
capital can flow in and out pretty
freely. And really they can only pick
two of those three. Uh they can't really
have all three. uh they have to
sacrifice one in order to maintain the
other two. Um and in a lot of countries
case uh you know they're running
monetary policy or fiscal policy that
results in their currency devaluing. Um
and they will often try to slow that
process by mandating some sort of fake
exchange rate. Uh and that's kind of
that's basically senior. the government
kind of gradually trying to extract
value from its citizens uh in ways that
are more opaque than taxes. Uh basically
debasement is historically a type of tax
that's just it's harder to measure,
harder to quantify. Most people in a
given country can't tell you what the
money supply growth rate of their
country is. Um it's just not something
people look up on a regular basis. Uh
it's actually more impactful than
official measures of inflation. Uh
because that's a number that's harder to
game. Um, and so as as currencies
devalue, often there are there are
political leaders that say, "Well, I
don't want the currency to devalue too
sharply because then it'll be more
apparent what's going on." So they try
to prop it up. Um, and then usually
release it all at once later when they
really don't have a choice. Um, and just
technology and awareness can kind of get
around that and give people more
optionality to to get out of that before
uh they're they're hit by it. You've
mentioned that money is how we store
purchasing power in the future. I love
that. And so that's why you know it's
really unfair for everyday people how
you know money supply increases so much
and you talk about how nothing stops the
train. I want I want you to maybe
explain to everybody what that means.
>> Right. Uh there's probably two separate
contexts for that. One is that every
every country has their own money supply
growth rate. uh on average developed
countries will be growing at
historically 6 to 8% per year. Obviously
during certain periods like you know 5
years ago there was accelerated growth
rates in most places but the the
multi-deade average for developed
markets is something like 6 to 8%. Uh in
developing countries it's it's often
over 10% many times way over 10%. Um uh
and so basically what that represents is
that everybody's savings are getting
debased at at this at whatever the rate
is for their environment. Uh but then
also not just their savings but also
every single contract denominated in
that currency is getting adjusted by the
money printer. And so, you know, if you
work as if you if you work for a wage uh
paid by someone else, um, and the money
supply is growing, it's up to you to try
to negotiate a higher wage, uh, every
year or, you know, more frequently
sometimes to try to keep up with that
debasement rate because just by doing
nothing, uh, your actual purchasing
power of your salary decreases, not just
your savings. uh and and that includes
business pricing. Uh that includes
supply contracts between businesses, you
know, businessto business type of
contracts. Uh and so periods where
there's like environments where there's
higher money supply growth rate, there's
generally less productivity because
there's more overhead that goes into
more frequent contract negotiations, uh
more slippage, more frictions, uh more
people just trying to get capital out of
that environment. Uh so it's harder to
invest. is it's less desirable for
capital to want to invest in that place
because it's harder to do the numbers
for what they're going to expect in
return. Uh and it just it damages
productivity. Uh when I talk about
nothing stops his train, I generally
specifically talk about US fiscal
deficits. Uh which is that we we're
running structurally large fiscal
deficits both in absolute terms and as a
percentage of GDP. And of course this
this has some global implications
because it's it's the global reserve
currency. uh and so it impacts uh dollar
debts and dollar savings uh around the
world. Um basically uh there were
periods of time in the US and elsewhere
where the environment is under monetary
dominance. So most new money supply is
being created by fractional reserve bank
lending. Uh but then there are other
times of fiscal dominance where uh the
the the large fiscal deficits that the
government's running um and when they
need to they monetize it meaning they
have their central bank increase the
money supply and buy more of their bonds
um that goes around the normal bank
lending channels uh and and basically
runs things hot and on average more
inflationary and that's what the US is
currently in. And the reason I use the
nothing stops his train uh statement
from originally from Breaking Bad, the
TV show, is that there's it's very hard
for the US to get out of the situation
anytime soon. So, we're talking 5 10
years. Uh I think they're still going to
be in a period of structurally high
fiscal deficits, which has implications
both for Americans and for the whole
world that that you know, and in part
uses the the dollar as a base ledger. So
if it's designed to grow and grow and
the number is just, you know, supposed
to get bigger by design, why do you
think there's a breaking point? Like why
are people talking about it? Why does it
sound scary?
>> Uh so I I generally argue that the the
breaking point to the extent it's there
at all is farther out than many bears
expect. Um because if I thought the
breaking point was near, I wouldn't use
the phrase nothing stops his train. The
the point is that it's both it's both
bearish and bullish because it's it's
it's basically saying that it's
unfixable in the near term, but it's
also not going to blow up in the near
term. It it's actually going to it's
going to persist for quite a while. Um
and that doesn't mean it's without
consequences during that time. The
consequences are happening the whole
way. all the things we just discussed as
you increase the money supply um and
especially as you do it through the
fiscal channel it basically means that
those who are on the right side of the
deficits uh are doing pretty well and
those who are not receiving the deficits
are the ones getting debased and not
being made up for in any given way. So
that includes on average younger
Americans that are say locked out of the
home buying market. Um and that also
includes the whole foreign sector that's
using dollars. um and include stable
coin holders because stable coin holders
are generally not getting interest on
their dollar holdings. Uh and yet the
dollar supply is growing at a pretty
meaningful rate per year. So they're
getting diluted. Um, and there's there's
this kind of this there's like a
hierarchy of capital access because if
if those who are well-connected
financially such as a US corporation,
uh, they will often issue dollar
liabilities and they'll buy something
more scarce. It could be Bitcoin, it
could be their own business equity, it
could be another company. They're buying
something that's higher yielding or more
more appreciating than the dollar and
they're, you know, they're willing to to
issue dollar debt with some interest to
pay for it. Uh then you have people in
other countries that say want to get out
of their local currency. It could maybe
the Nigerian currency for example.
They're getting into dollars, but
they're often not getting a yield on
their dollar. So they're still being
debased relative to those that are in a
position to buy even scarcer assets and
that are shorting the dollar often to do
it like Micro Strategy is doing. They
issue various dollar denominated credit
liabilities to get more Bitcoin and
arbitrage the fact that over the long
run Bitcoin is outperforming the dollar.
Uh, and the unfortunate thing about all
that is it really kind of widens the
gap. Um, because if you're in a position
to own the scarcest things and short fit
currencies, you're doing pretty well.
And if you're the one holding uh
currencies and not in a position to
really be issuing all these these credit
instruments or or shorting the
currencies, you're getting gradually to
base and you're on this treadmill trying
to keep up. And that's that's kind of
the issue behind broken money. Um that's
why the you know that's a big reason why
the world has these kind of issues at at
the current time and technology is
gradually addressing that. Uh but of
course it takes time, it takes network
effects, it takes education. Uh and it
it's it's ongoing.
>> It's broken because it's unfair. But
what about for people that actually have
assets? It favors them. they're happy
that, you know, everything that we
talked about is happening because it
just pumps up the um price of my asset,
right?
>> Yeah. And if you're in a position for
it, like I I'm in a position where the
the more the US wants to debase itself,
I'm okay because I'm short the dollar
and I'm long other things. So, if they
want to debase it, that's fine. Uh it's
not necessarily good for societal
health, though. I'd rather live in a
society that's more harmonious and
functional than one that's in disarray,
but that those in the say the top 10%
that have, you know, the best access to
to doing things like that are are
flourishing and others are, you know, it
becomes dangerous to go anywhere because
the, you know, it's a it's a messy
environment now. So in the grand scheme
of things, you generally
it's better to have a fair environment
that you're doing well in than unfair
environment that you're still
beneficiary of. Uh because that's kind
of a it's it might feel good in the
short term. Uh but longer term that's
that's worse. Um, and one of the things
I kind of argue is that it's it's sort
of an inevitable um, outcome of the
mismatch we find ourselves in for this
past century and a half, which when you
have fast transaction speeds, slow
settlements, uh, we're going to become
very reliant on middlemen, banks and
central banks, and we have been uh, and
and there really for for a century and a
half, there really was no alternative.
Uh, if you wanted to send money
globally, how would you do it otherwise?
Um but now uh because of of Bitcoin and
and for some countries because of stable
coins they can get outside their at
least their local monopoly and still
relying on the dollar system but at
least at least outside of their local
one with Bitcoin being outside all of
them there's now more tools and as those
tools get five times bigger and more
liquid and more understood and then 10
times bigger and more liquid understood
it can gradually address this problem.
Uh, another way I kind of put it is
that, you know, for for a lot of
history, people of course get rewarded
for doing something very productive, you
know, building the railroads or
inventing electricity. And of course,
that's that's a good thing. Uh, in the
in the current era in kind of this
latestage fiat environment, um, the
biggest rewards generally go to those
that are arbitrageing the system the
most, uh, or at least the the lowest
path to get there. So, of course, it's
still if you can invent the next, you
know, hundred billion dollar idea,
that's still the path toward the most
riches. But generally speaking, if you
want to get fairly wealthy, it was
better to go to Wall Street than
anywhere else. It was better to go into
Wall Street than be an engineer or a
doctor uh or in many cases startup
founder, unless you're going to be the
top 1% of them. uh you know, if you're
going to go somewhere that that the
financial sector was just kind of a
brain drain, drawing so many people
toward it because one of the best things
you could do is borrow at 2% and buy
assets that are that are going up at a
at a at a you know significant rate and
and otherwise kind of do financial
engineering. Um and that's generally
where you get more issues. And I think
that over time as Bitcoin gets bigger um
as technology kind of levels the playing
field I think that arbitrage starts to
shrink and return things more toward you
know the engineers the doctors uh any
anyone who's in a position where they're
actually improving people's lives in a
meaningful way and therefore uh
benefiting themselves in the process
versus those that are just kind of
arbitrageing uh inefficiencies or
centralizations uh in in the current
system. I know that you like writing
sci-fi. Is that correct?
>> Yes. Yeah, it's fun.
>> I'd like to hear. Okay. Your imagination
at work. Two versions of an idea,
monetary system. First is the most
realistic, the one that we might be able
to see within our lifetime. And the
second one is something, you know, more
sci-fi, something that might happen if
we start fresh on Mars or, you know,
that's like the perfect scenario. What
would it look like?
>> I think the the realistic scenario for
the foreseeable future is a gradual
kind of we've had this kind of
fracturization where the whole world
kind of used to at a for a period of
time use gold and silver as money and
now we've got 180 different currencies.
It's it's this fracturing that happened
and I think the most realistic path is
that that starts to condense again and
starts to shrink uh where the smallest
weakest currencies basically stop
existing uh because there's no reason
for people to be stuck in them anymore
as their options improve and as uh more
uh you know more internet connectivity
goes everywhere, more understanding goes
everywhere, this has time to play out,
people get into stable coins, they get
into Bitcoin, uh they get into a larger
local currency
uh rather than whatever the smallest one
is. Uh and so this I think over years
and decades gradually starts to condense
uh and people have more options and
they're able to get into those better
assets um at at more of an even playing
field. Uh and so I think the world looks
like growing Bitcoin uh and then still
coexisting alongside fiat currencies. Uh
but that the the the the fiat side is
gradually getting less in number uh and
people are more aware of not sticking
too much value in it and starting to
either hold other assets like Bitcoin
even pricing things in Bitcoin
eventually. That's I think the the
nearer term o over years and decades our
lifetime. I I think the ideal scenario
is is just basically outside out of fiat
currency altogether. Uh which is that
we've we've closed the speed gap. We no
longer need these big centralized
ledgers at least the foundation. Um
they're still sometimes used for
centralization higher layers. Uh they
can increase efficiency and they can
provide services. Um but they don't need
to be running the core layer itself. Uh
so whether we're on Earth or Mars, uh
basically having some sort of
foundational blockchain on Earth it's
it's Bitcoin. Maybe on Mars it'll be
different because of the the delay the
the the time delay of of um signals
between them. Um basically a
foundational currency that uh is more
transparent uh more fair um doesn't have
all of these host of issues I've I've
described so far. Uh and that that and
people grow up in that environment and
that is just a normal thing. Um, one of
the, it's kind of crazy how fast
technology changed in a century. So,
people went from like literally in our
early grandparents lifetimes using gold
and silver uh or having money at least
backed by it where they they think of it
as proxies for gold and silver uh to
just floating paper currency. And if you
told people, you know, like these, you
know, in the future, in a couple
decades, people would just be using
paper as money or or digital bits that
that are not backed by anything as
money. Uh it would have sounded crazy uh
to a lot of people. Uh and then yet now
we grow up and think that's normal. Uh
and I I think that the future world is
one where people grow up and you know
something like Bitcoin exists and that's
normal. And the idea of just like uh
money that that is created out of
nothing and that people earn their
paycheck in it and save it, that sounds
weird to people as like that's a crazy
thing that that humans used to do but we
don't have to do anymore. That that
that's I think the state we want to get
to.
>> That kind of wipes out the stock market
too. If the money supply is fixed then
is there a stock market or any financial
activities, investments? because a lot
of people nowadays invest because they
want to keep up the purchasing power.
But what happens if the money supply is
fixed?
>> Uh they're still investing in that
world. Uh I I think basically becomes
more optional. Uh because it becomes a
way to take on risk to increase your um
uh net worth rather than something you
have to do just to maintain uh your net
worth. Uh and so basically and you know
Jeff Booth and others have made this
point that when money is weak people
monetize other things. they go and buy
extra property, they go and buy gold,
they go and buy fine art, they go and
buy stocks, um, whatever the case may
be. As long as as long as, you know,
they're trying to get out of their local
debasing fiat currency. If money is
strong, uh, like back in, you know, when
it was gold or if if it's Bitcoin, uh,
then the hurdle rate for wanting to get
into other things is higher. Um, now
it's not zero. It's not like infinite
because you if if there's a profitable
business or a business that has a good
chance of becoming profitable, you can
still earn more of the base uh layer by
you know investing in something that is
creating value and and you know
basically extracting value from
elsewhere because it it it's doing
something better than the existing
system. So there's still winners and
losers in that system but instead of
this kind of ongoing debasement that
happens in the background is actually
the real value uh moving around. I want
to talk about you because while I was
doing research, something kept on coming
up. It says you grew up in poverty and
at times even without a home. I don't
know if that's true. You can tell me the
story. Um, growing up, I want to know
what your relationship with money is.
Um, when do you start learning to invest
or save? What was the financial
education like?
>> Sure. So, I when I was living with my
mother, uh, we were homeless for a
period of time. So we lived in homeless
shelters. Uh like first we lived with a
relative, then we lived in homeless
shelters. Uh then we lived in like worse
homeless shelters. Then we lived briefly
in a motel. And then we briefly were in
a car. And that's when I went to live
with my father. So I I exited being
homeless. Um and I grew up then in a in
a trailer park, which was an upgrade. Um
and at that time I I became way
interested in saving and investing. uh
which I guess is not surprising because
I was I was in that kind of more chaotic
environment the environment of scarcity
uh and so when I you know was this was
when I was say
>> four to six I was homeless so by the
time I was seven eight I was growing up
in a in a trailer park um but things
were more stable there and so when I
would when I would get like you know
Christmas presents or birthday presents
and have some cash I would I would
generally save it uh I got into coin
collecting so gold and silver coins I
guess I was an early gold bug uh like in
the '9s. Um and then by the time I was a
late teenager, I got into equities. Uh I
started to buy stocks. Um and so I I
think that you know a lot of times there
is a silver lining to to something um
that is on its surface a negative thing.
Uh which for me was it got me interested
uh in thinking about the future, saving
for the future. uh and of course it is
now the career path that I that I focus
on is uh not only investing but but
studying the very nature of what money
is, how to make good money, um what is
the history of money, how can money
change to benefit more people. Uh so I I
try to look on the bright side of
everything.
>> Do you would you say your investment
style lean towards more conservative?
Because if you've gone through that, you
don't want to lose your money. I think
it it has leaned conservative for my
age. Um, and so many, you know, like I I
don't really go all into anything no
matter the conviction level, uh, because
I never put myself in a position where
I'm focusing entirely on one asset. Um,
and so, and I think because I have that
background with gold and silver, uh,
more so than mo most people my age, uh,
it's not something I just say want to
own zero of, even though of course way
more focused elsewhere. Um, and so I I
do think that there's always some degree
of diversification uh, for me. Um, which
I is probably part of that background.
Um, but I still when I have a high
conviction on something, I still put a
big percentage of my time and capital
into it. Uh, and so, you know, based on
most standards, the the amount that I've
kind of say focused on Bitcoin and the
percentage of my net worth that
Bitcoin's become and as it kind of does
its crazy volatility, like I, you know,
I was on stage at Pacific Bitcoin in
November 2022 while FTX was crashing uh,
and we were having a great time. So,
it's not like I I and it's because of my
more conservative style of doing things
that even when it seems like the world's
crashing and volatility is happening,
that's where the benefit of that
approach happens where I'm I'm in a
position to say buy more or otherwise
just not really be that concerned about
the volatility because um you know the
whole net worth isn't necessarily
fluctuating by that percentage even
though a big chunk might be. Um, and I
think it helps think clearly um, and be
helpful in that regard.
>> Um, May this year, you posted, "My
16-year-old Hyundai is finally starting
to fail, and you decided to join the
rich life and get a Toyota."
>> Yes.
>> Um, first thought, I was like, damn,
Hyundai lasts for a long time. And then
second thought was, um, I'm curious just
how your values and how you view money
evolves over time. like when people get
to a certain level of wealth, they're
like, I need to enjoy life. I might want
to upgrade my car, my house, and stuff
like that. What is your view on that?
>> Uh, so I mean, I think people should
pursue their passions. There there's
certain types of things that I think
make sense more than others, which is
generally speaking, it's not good to
chase status symbols. So, if something
is not something that you personally
enjoy, but you want to signal to others,
that's usually not the the best use of
money. Um, often a really good use of
money is curing pain points. Uh, and
people have different pain points. So,
for me, uh, I didn't really care much
about my car. I don't do a ton of
driving. Uh, I'm not a car enthusiast.
It's different than if someone is a car
enthusiast. Uh, and so for me, it was
kind of like it was just, you know,
point A to point B. Uh, spend as little
value on as possible, especially when I
was, you know, I went through college, I
had student loans. uh then I was working
as an entry- level engineer and then
gradually kind of working my way up the
hierarchy. Uh so by having just this
boring car with no car payments, uh it
helped me save elsewhere. Um but then
even when I when I was in a position to
to upgrade it with no problem, I was
like, well that's that's time and
hassle. Um it's nice having a car that
if someone bangs into it, I don't care.
Uh my my concern is elsewhere. Um, and
so I kind of took pride in the in the in
the, you know, driving a 60-y old
Hyundai until I couldn't do it anymore.
Uh, but at the same time, for example,
like for me, a pain point is traveling.
Um, and so I I I would invest in in
better seats or just better better ways
of traveling around. Uh, which which
many people might say would be
excessive, whereas for me, it's like
that's solving a problem enough that I
actually want to go on the trip that I
might have otherwise not gone on. Uh so
it's I think it's my main kind of advice
to people would be be conscious of where
spending money actually gives you an
impact uh rather than just do things on
autopilot because it's considered
normal. So it's often considered normal
that if you reach a certain wealth level
your house has to look a certain way,
your condo has to look a certain way,
your car has to look a certain way,
you're you're wearing certain things
that signal, you know, people people get
kind of caught up in that treadmill. uh
you don't have to do that and instead
you can just pick and choose which which
areas actually don't matter to you and
which areas are actually places where
spending money makes a really big
difference and makes you happier.
>> I want to share a story with you. So
I've actually spent some time in Egypt
and you're talking about how you know
your car you're not afraid of your car
being bumped. Every car in Cairo looks
like it just came out of a bumper car
match. It's crazy. Super wild.
>> Yeah. I was working on a school project
where we could choose any topic we
wanted and I really wanted to go to
Egypt. So I just told my professor and
my parents that you know I I was doing
research there and that was during the
second Egyptian revolution
and um that was when I realized I and I
saw how resilient people were and Egypt
has always um hold a very special place
in my heart and I want to um know your
relationship. You have roots and
families and friends in Egypt, right?
>> Yeah. My husband's originally from
there. Uh, and so all of my in-laws are
Egyptian and of course I have a lot of
friends in Egypt. So we we spend part of
each year there. Uh, and and I agree
with you, it's a very resilient place.
Uh, it kind of shows how how life can
continue even as things are chaotic
around you. Uh and then even just in the
past 5 years so where there's been you
know say way less political instability
uh they were dealing at one point with
38% inflation
um you know the money supply growing by
20 plus% per year uh on a sustained
basis uh and you know life was still
going on there's still people doing all
the all the normal things uh that you
expect even though people a lot of
people were in in pain um and I often
just use as an example of broken money
um because it it shows how the ledger
that people are kind of forced to use uh
can really create these malinvestments
or headwinds against productivity so
that through no fault of their own there
are frictions and and one of the saddest
things is like I mean I know I know for
example doctors in Egypt um where they
were just you know how do they save
money they go to the gray market they
buy physical dollars they stash them in
their apartment and that you know in the
in the 21st century that's the that's
what they consider the best savings
technology available to them and then
and then many of them would you as soon
as they get the opportunity they travel
elsewhere uh to try to get more income
uh because the economic activity you
like optionality in Egypt is is more
limited and it's it's often just because
there's there's these frictions to these
headwinds uh they don't have to be there
um so I I you know it's I I think for a
A lot of investors especially traveling
really broadens your view of of things
and gives you insights that people that
are uh doing things just in their own
country don't necessarily have. And I
think it's I think it's really valuable.
>> And now we have AI. It sounds like it
sounds so different like like two
different world. We have AI and some
people argue that you know AI will be so
productive where everything will be
almost free. like everything will be so
cheap it will be almost free and we will
have so much time that we don't know
what to do with ourselves. Is this
statement true or or false? And how
would that change inflation and money?
Well, it's interesting people there are
people making somewhat similar arguments
a century ago as we entered kind of the
industrial revolution uh at scale where
they said you know right now the work
week is high but in the future it'll
it'll get down to maybe 10 15 hours a
week and people have all this free time
and instead people are working often
more than more than you know 50 years
ago in many cases. Um and there was this
you know technology greatly changes what
we spend our time on. And so for
example, it used to be that a very high
percentage of people worked in
agriculture. Uh but as people invented
tractors and all these other equipment,
uh we automated you know 90 plus% of
that. So now something like 1 or 2% of
people work in agriculture and feed the
other 98% uh because of that massive
productivity gain. Uh and that of course
extended to textiles. You know the
percentage of people that have to work
in textiles has just dramatically
fallen. uh then people go into into
other fields and I I do think that we're
entering an era where that will start
happening is is already happening to
some types of white collar work which is
that things that used to require a lot
of human labor um not that they
necessarily need zero human labor but
that they they can make it so that one
or two people can do the work of 10
people um because they're overseeing a
lot of automation to do certain things
that used to be very labor intensive.
Uh, and that of course can be disruptive
when it happens quickly as it as it was
in the past. Um, but then it it it um
gives more people time to to do
elsewhere. Um, the the big risk where I
think it starts to maybe change the game
uh where I wouldn't be too dismissive uh
is that um it can eventually get to a
point where something like 50% of people
would not necessarily be able to do
something in any capacity that machine
can't do. uh and therefore might have
trouble securing economic stability for
themselves and and their family. Um and
it becomes very hard to get out of that
cycle. Um that that's probably the risk
I would worry about the most in that
capacity. So I I I do think that we're
overall entering a period where we're
there's a whole new stack of things we
can automate uh that makes those things
more abundant and cheaper. Uh but that
comes with disruption. I wouldn't I I
don't really hold the view that like
things are going to be nearly free
because there still is a very big
physical component to life. It's still
energy intensive, material intensive, uh
to build a house, to transport things,
uh to to to make highquality goods, uh
to provide highquality health care. Um a
lot of that still has a very real input
that AI can't you know software can
iterate very quickly, but anything in
the real world takes time. It takes like
20 years to bring on a copper mine from
scratch for example. Um you know even
even manufacturing is very energy energy
intensive. You know in the US right now
of course as we try to ramp up all these
all this uh data center for AI uh
there's like a there's like a five plus
year backlog uh of getting electrical
parts often from China to to build some
of the electric electrical transmission
things we need or data center things we
need uh just to do that. And that's like
the bottlenecks that people that work
strictly in AI might not first think
about and they say, "Oh, wait. This
actually touches the real world. We
actually have to figure out where where
we gonna get the copper. Where are we
going to get the, you know, the the the
uh transformer? Where are we going to
get the electricity on a stable
inexpensive basis?" So there still is a
real world constraint and it just kind
of changes uh in many cases where we
work and where we spend our time. There
is this narrative that I've seen quite
often online these days. Um the biggest
asset that rich people have are poor
people and the system the education help
produce employee and the rich intend to
keep it that way. What do you think?
>> I think there's there's truth to that.
Um,
>> you know, as kind of a as we enter the
industrial revolution and different
countries entered at different kind of
phases, but as as a as a place enters an
industrial revolution, um, at first it
becomes you a lot of the education
system reorients around a couple key
things. While the parents are at work,
uh, someone has to watch the kids. Uh,
and so instead of the family doing it
themselves, we kind of we kind of, um,
scale the process up. Uh and so we make
schooling and then while they're at
school we we we train the the children
so when they grow up uh they are uh
ready for jobs uh in in that environment
and we generally don't trained things
like how to become an entrepreneur
uh or or you know things like that. It's
basically how to how to pass all the
tests, how to follow instructions, how
to know enough things that you know
depending on what your capacities are
you can you can you can work in these
different areas. Uh, so I do think that
there's some truth to that. Um, often it
it's kind of the byproduct of no one's
necessarily intentionally designing it
that way or at least not always. And
instead it just it kind of people's
individual incentives kind of click that
into place until you get to a new
technological era where that doesn't
make sense anymore and people either
want new things or new things become
possible. Um, and you know another thing
is going back to the kind of the prior
point about ledgers. Um, part of it is
that the the biggest I would say one of
the biggest resources that rich people
have is the ability to short the
currency uh at at cheap rates. So, if
you're impoverished and you borrow,
you're often borrowing in say credit
cards, you're paying a very high
interest rate. Uh but if you're a well-
capitalized individual or corporation,
uh you're often borrowing at a very low
interest rate uh and with very good
terms like it doesn't it's not going to
be called away from you at an
inopportune time and force you to sell
due to volatility. Uh and what that
means is that if there are people that
uh are you know for for lack of better
options holding currency that you're
shorting
um you know you're you're kind of
gradually extracting value from them. Uh
so that's kind of an indirect way where
the wealthy benefit from the the poor uh
because they're they're shorting the
thing that other people are earning
their wages in uh and that that creates
an unhealthy dynamic. So I think part of
that is the broken money itself.
um that doesn't have to be there. It
that can be fixed in my opinion. Things
be made more transparent and a more even
playing field. Uh and there are other
things that are maybe just more
entrenched uh that as a society develops
and goes through a certain phase, there
are certain um frictions that happen uh
that we can hopefully move past and
improve.
>> What is your advice for an average
person that's watching? uh person could
be watching our conversation and
freaking out. What is your advice to
them?
>> Uh I depends on where they are in life
of course. Uh advice will differ. I'd
say the two main things one would be
financial which is basically try to try
to own scarce things and then if
possible short uh unscar things um you
know safely um that's kind of the rule
of thumb is always always kind of ask
the question am I being diluted
uh and if so how can I stop that from
happening or minimize that from
happening so if you're holding an asset
where the supply is growing at 7% and
you're getting 4% interest on it you're
you're getting diluted at a net rate of
about 3%. You're owning a smaller share
of that ledger from holding it over
time. Um, and that that applies whether
it's gold, whether it's stable coins,
whether it's local currency. Uh,
sometimes if it's stock, uh, always ask
the question, am I getting diluted uh,
relative to the whole pie of whatever
this thing is? Uh, and if it's possible,
can I short something that is getting
diluted? So, I'm benefiting from that
dilution and owning scarcer things. Um,
from a a more a broader perspective, I
think that as you know, as AI and other
things can make certain digital things
and certain certain repetition uh things
automated, um, it ironically brings back
some of the real world expertise. Uh, so
one thing to keep in mind is that
portable AI is like a thousand times
harder than data center AI. Uh, so like
>> explain that.
>> Yeah. So the brain the brain runs on
about 20 watts of power. So less than an
incandescent light bulb. Um and some of
our top supercomputers like there's
different estimates for how many
calculations per second a brain does.
There's there's you know you can look at
the number of neurons and number of
connections and then the the and there's
estimates and only kind of in this past
several years have our best
supercomputers reached roughly the level
that that most people think that the
number of calculations a brain does. Now
obviously in certain areas it's way
better like you know it can calculate
you know a million times uh you know a
billion times a trillion faster than we
can do. Um but if you if you consider
how much signal you're taking in so all
the different senses you're doing all
the different things your brain's doing
to stand upright to to understand the
world around it while consciously
thinking about something and solving a
problem that's actually really high
bandwidth high processing um thing that
you're doing that's actually pretty hard
for computers to do. Um, and those
supercomputers that kind of obviously in
some ways surpass humans, but in other
ways just are still catching up to
humans. They operate on something like
20 megawws of power compared to 20 watts
of power. So they they need about a
million times more energy
>> uh to do something like the same amount
of calculations per second. Obviously
again in certain areas they're they're
way better. Certain areas they're worse.
Um but so when you think of something
that an AI data center can do then the
question is well if I want to put that
into a robot how hard is that because
now in a in a robot uh then power really
matters something that something that
you you know that might take kilowatts
of energy to do you want to happen in in
watts uh or you know uh and so uh
anything that that involves
>> a data center or that involves robots in
a very controlled environment like in a
manufacturing facility
that is way easier than all many things
out in the field. Uh because out in the
field that power density really matters
uh and so it takes a lot more time and
and technology to to compress that uh
like Moore's law. Uh and uh the
everything gets way harder. So, it's
it's it's easier to automate an
industrial arm building cars in a in a
clean environment where technicians can
help with edge cases as needed, uh,
versus having a car drive itself across
all manner of of roads in the world and,
you know, avoiding hitting a dog and
being able to navigate every type of
sign that's out there. Um, and all the
edge cases, uh, and and, you know,
things like that. Like you mentioned
Egypt. Imagine trying to self-drive in
in Cairo, for example. Uh that's, you
know, maybe in a very clean uh uh
environment. It's it's possible, but the
messier you get, the harder it is to do.
Um and that's where where humans still
have an edge, and I think we're going to
have an edge for quite a while. So,
ironically, some really skilled
bluecollar work that's out in the field,
I think, is some of the most resistant
to uh AI uh taking jobs uh and and also
just being a very well-rounded person.
uh and using the fact that you know you
you're you're a portable person, you're
energy efficient uh and so you might be
able to compete with a data center on
many things but you can go into the real
world and and you know affect things in
a way that is far less energy efficient
for AI alone to do at least any time you
know in in the next couple decades.
>> You know that ending is so powerful I
love it. Okay. So, the publisher want me
to do something. Um, we're giving away
three copies of your book and I want
people to maybe comment um down below
what they learned like what they learned
uh from this conversation because I've
learned so much and we're going to
select three viewers to give this book
away.
Broken money.
>> Yeah. Um, thank you so much. It was such
a great conversation.
>> Please come back soon. Happy birthday.